Guide to the Mordecai Hillel Kroshnitz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mordecai Hillel Kroshnitz papers
1936-1997
1960-1990
MS 2013
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.46
(6 boxes)
The papers contain between two and three thousand handwritten or typed documents including letters, poems, and drafts of articles and lectures. Many of the letters are sent from Yiddish authors and institutions around the world. The papers also include clippings and issues of periodicals with writings by Kroshnitz, reviews of his work, and source material for his work.
Ḳroshnits, Mordekhai
Scope and Contents
The papers contain between two and three thousand handwritten or typed documents including letters, poems, and drafts of articles and lectures. Most of the papers are letters sent to Kroshnitz or items he wrote when he lived in Israel after World War II, except for a few photocopies of articles he had published in Yiddish newspapers in Poland in the 1930's. Many of the letters are from Yiddish authors and institutions around the world, including M. (Moshe) Bick, Chaim Grade, K. Fiszbin, Menke Katz, Avraham Patt, and others. The papers also include clippings and issues of periodicals with writings by Kroshnitz, reviews of his work, and source material for his work. There are notes for a lecture on humor, a speech to the International Conference on Yiddish Language and Culture, and materials for speeches and articles about Yiddish writers, notably Sholem Aleichem, Sholem Asch, Sh. (Shelomoh) Berlinski, M. (Moshe) Bick, Dr. [Shlomo?] Bickel, David Einhorn, Menke Katz, Yehoshua Monik Lederman, Mani Leib, H. Leivick, Itzik Manger, Nachman Mayzel, Mendele Mokher Sefarim, Levi Papiernikov, David Pinski, Melech Ravitch, David Rodin, Eliezer Steinbarg, Shyfra Werber, and Yehoash. In addition, there are notes for presentations about Jewish communities destroyed in the Holocaust, including the communities of Zamość and Częstochowa, Poland. Kroshnitz's journal contains poems, various notes, the text of a speech he gave on his eightieth birthday, and a eulogy for "my friend, Menke Katz."
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Judaica Collection Curator, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
Mordecai Hillel Kroshnitz was a Yiddish journalist and writer who was born in Baranowice, Belarus in 1915. During World War II he escaped the Nazis and joined the Red Army. After the war he returned to Poland and was active in Zionist-Socialist organizations and causes. Kroshnitz moved to Israel with his family in 1949, where he continued his activism in Israel's organization of trade unions, the Histadrut, and in Yiddish literary circles. Through his work and personal correspondence he maintained connections with the other writers throughout the world who created the post-war Yiddish literary scene. Kroshnitz was the author of numerous articles and four books: Eygns (1963), Natur un Mentsh (1965), Erd (1967), and Doyres (1969). He also edited two Yizkor (memorial) books: Krasnobrod (1956) and Lubṭsh un Delaṭiṭsh yizker-bukh (1971); as well as Ḥeyfe [Haifa]: yorbukh far liṭeraṭur un ḳunsṭ (1963-1969), which he co-edited together with David Rodin.
Arrangement
The papers are loosely arranged without changes to the original organization despite inconsistencies. Descriptions of contents are preliminary, not comprehensive. Clippings and issues of periodicals that were in portfolios have been placed in the corresponding folders, while other clippings and periodicals are in a separate box.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ḳroshnits, Mordekhai, 1915-1998 -- Archives
- Inventory
  - Speeches on the communities of Zamość and Częstochowa, Poland, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Handwritten texts of talks presented to Holocast memorial gatherings in Israel.
  - Anna and Leyb Rubinlicht Prize for Yiddish Literature and Culture, Israeli Association of Yiddish Writers and Journalists, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Materials, including poster, letters of congratulations, draft of speech, and newspaper clippings, primarily relate to Kroshnitz's receipt of the prize. There is some other unrelated material as well.
  - Posters announcing talks by Kroshnitz and notes for those talks, Circa 1965-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, mostly regarding works by Kroshnitz, Circa 1950-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    There are many letters from other authors and institutions, including the writer Jonas Turkow and YIVO librarian Dina Abramovitz, thanking Kroshnitz for giving them copies of his book.
  - Articles, clippings, and drafts of articles and book reviews, 1962-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    There are materials on topics of interest to Kroshnitz, as well as items he wrote. The latter includes "Is it good for the Jews?", which discusses the Jewish vote in the upcoming election in the United States between Nixon and McGovern, in an issue of Di Tsukunft.
  - Notes, drafts, and newspaper clippings with source material for articles and lectures about Yiddish writers, 1962-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Authors discussed include Sholem Aleichem, Mendele Mokher Sefarim, David Pinski, Eliezer Steinbarg, Nachman Mayzel, Yehoash, H. Leivick, Sholem Asch, David Einhorn, Itzik Manger, Melech Ravitch, Mani Leib, Dr. [Shlomo?] Bickel, and Menke Katz.
  - Notes, drafts, and newspaper clippings with source material for articles and lectures, 1968-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    These materials include notes for a lecture on humor, a speech to the International Conference on Yiddish Language and Culture, and materials for speeches and articles about Yiddish writers, including Sh. (Shelomoh) Berlinski, Yehoshua Monik Lederman, Shyfra Werber, David Rodin, Levi Papiernikov, and M. (Moshe) Bick.
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, with some notes, Circa 1960-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Printed articles by and about Kroshnitz, 1936-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Unpublished works, Circa 1960-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Works by other writers sent to Kroshnitz, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1954-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    One document with the heading "Answers of Mordekhai Kroshnitz" outlines the chronology of his life. (CV/resume?)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Many of the correspondents are Yiddish writers, including Moshe Bik, Chaim Grade, K. Fiszbin, Avraham Patt and Menke Katz.
  - Journal and miscellaneous writings, 1977-1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1964-1970, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Folḳ, ṿelṭ un medine, 1976, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Lebns-fragn, 1977-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Liṭerarishe hefṭn, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Der Onheyb, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Problemen, 1973-1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Problemot = Problemen, 1963-1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Shurot, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Di Tsukunft, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Undzer dor, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Undzer eygn vinkl, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Yidishe Kultur, 1986, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 12)